Hebrew Home and Hospital Collection 0008.002.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Hebrew Home and Hospital
1898-2012
0008.002.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
1.5 Cubic feet 3 boxes 15 oversize framed documents
At the end of the last century, the women of the Jewish community banded together to create a wide variety of social services. One of their primary concerns was the care of the aged, and in 1898 they formed the Hebrew Ladies' Sick Benefit Association, probably an auxiliary of the Hebrew Sick Benefit Association. In 1901, the women pledged to pay five cents per week into a fund towards the building of a home for elders. They also went door to door collecting nickels each week from members of the community, carrying the money in handkerchiefs and earning the name "the handkerchief brigade." By 1907, they had raised enough money to purchase a large home at 33 Wooster Street that became the Hebrew Old People's Home.
In 1911, the group changed its name to the Hebrew Ladies' Old Peoples' Home Association and began raising money for an expansion. By 1919, however, the Wooster Street facility could no longer meet community demand, and a mansion at 276 Washington Street was purchased. A large annex was eventually built. The number of elders under the care of the home grew so great that volunteer administration and maintenance was no longer feasible. In 1929 the first paid staff members were hired.
By the1940s, the Home was again too small for the community's needs, and fundraising for a new facility began again. The new facility was completed in 1955 on Tower Avenue and received the name "Hebrew Home for the Aged." Eventually the Tower Avenue facility, responding to the needs of its constituents, became an actual chronic disease hospital.
As the Jewish population moved west into West Hartford, Bloomfield, and Simsbury, most of the local Jewish institutions moved, as well. The Home, now called Hebrew Home and Hospital, joined them, moving to a site off of Bloomfield Avenue in 1989. The Home remains one of the prime local Jewish institutions today, a source of pride for the community.
Arrangement note
This collection is an accretion of many small donations.
Bloomfield Avenue, Hartford, CT; Handkerchief Brigade; Hebrew Home and Hospital; Hebrew Ladies Sick Benefit; Hebrew Ladies' Old People's Association; Tower Avenue, Hartford, CT; Washington Street, Hartford, CT; Wooster Street, Hartford, CT
- Series I: Records, A-B
  - Advertising, Undated (Box 1)
  - Anniversaries, Undated (Box 1)
  - Annual Meetings, Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Board Members, Undated (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Fundraising/Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Fundraising/Strawberry Festival, Undated (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Meeting Minutes re: History of Hartford (1965) (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Meeting Programs, Undated (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Volunteer Activities, Undated (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors/Members, Undated (Box 1)
  - Board of Director/Minutes, Undated (Box 1)
  - Buildings/33 Wooster Street, Hartford [1911?1919] (Box 1)
  - Buildings/276 Washington Street, Hartford [1919?1955] (Box 1)
  - Buildings/615 Tower Avenue, Hartford [1955?1989] (Box 1)
  - Buildings/1 Abrahms Boulevard, West Hartford [1989? ] (Box 1)
  - Buildings/1 Abrahms Boulevard, West Hartford [1989? ] (Box 1)
- Series II: Records, C-M
  - Constitution and By?Laws (1901, 1947, 1952, 1960), 1901-1960 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Education/Workshops, undated (Box 2)
  - Financial Information, undated (Box 2)
  - Founders, undated (Box 2)
  - Fundraising, undated (Box 2)
  - Fundraising/Sophie Tucker Benefit Shows, undated (Box 2)
  - Government Funding, undated (Box 2)
  - Historical Highlights, undated (Box 2)
  - Institutional Activities/Programs for Residents and Day Clients, undated (Box 2)
  - Lecture Series, undated (Box 2)
- Series III: Records, N-Z
  - Newsletters/Family Newsletter, 2000s, 2000-2009 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Happenings, 1980?1981 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1952, 1965?1981, 1952-1981 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1984?1986 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/ Highlights, 1987?1988 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1989?1991 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1992?1995 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1996­1997 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 2002-2003 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Highlights, 2004-2005 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters/Image '93, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1930s-1940s, 1930-1949 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950s-1960s, 1950-1969 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1970s-1980s, 1970-1989 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 2000s, 2000-2009 (Box 3)
  - Open House Celebration, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Photocopies/copies of newspaper articles related to the Hebrew Home, undated (Box 3)
  - Reports/Report from the President …on the Impact of the Nursing Shortage, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Residents, undated (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook/Anna Fichman's Scrapbook, undated (Box 3)
  - Staff Members, undated (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Auxiliary/"Honorary Board," 1967 (Box 1)
  - Auxiliary/Members, undated (Box 1)
  - Buildings/33 Wooster Street, undated (Box 1)
  - Buildings/276 Washington Street, undated (Box 1)
  - Buildings/276 Washington Street, undated (Box 1)
  - Buildings/615 Tower Avenue, undated (Box 1)
  - Founders, undated (Box 1)
  - Fundraising/Sophie Tucker's Benefit Shows, undated (Box 1)
  - Historical Highlights, undated (Box 1)
  - Residents, undated (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook of Anna Fichman, Auxiliary president, filed in main box. Use preservation photocopies for research, not the original., undated
  - Scrapbook of Lillian Krinsky, Junior League of Hebrew Ladies' Old Peoples' Home, filed in separate box, undated
- Artifacts
  - 3 badges and ribbons created for Abrahms Blvd. facility groundbreaking, 1986 Badge created for Abrahms Blvd. facility fundraising; "Keep the Promise" Souvenir Hagaddah from Jerusalem, ca 1896, probably the possession of a former resident
- Oversized Materials
  - Some oversized documents have been photocopied and stored in the Oversize Documents/Organizations box; the copies have been incorporated into the main document collection., undated
  - Other documents that have been framed are located on shelf G?6. These consist of very large framed resolutions commemorating various individuals, 1940-1950s., undated
- Commemorative Resoultions/Miscellaneous Other
  - 1947 list of founders, officers, etc.
  - Board of Directors/copy of large framed commemorative picture with medallion photos of the directors, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Abramson, David, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Freidman, Joseph, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Friedman, Joseph M., undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Ginsberg, Fannie Gilman, in oversize drawer 2, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Katzman, Bela, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Laschever, Rose, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Sherman, Isadore, undated
  - Commemorative resolution/Weinstein, Mrs. Maurice, undated
  - Founders, very good quality photo, undated
  - Contributors to the building fund, 1925-1926, with names of many prominent people,including Sophier Tucker and Beatrice Auerbach
  - Other/Businesses/Kashman Specialty Market/interior, 1920s, 1920-1929
  - Other/Businesses/Whelan Drugs/Samuel Berson, 1950s?, 1950-1959
  - Other/Education/Hartford Public High School Hopkins debating club, 1909-1910
  - Other/Education/Hartford Public High School Hopkins debating club, 1916
  - Other/Education/HPHL, Class of 1912
  - Other/Education/HPHL, Class of 1922A
  - Other/Education/Sports/Football Team, 1916
  - Other/Family History/genealogy charts, undated
  - Other/floor plan of Emanuel 25th anniversary, undated
  - Other/Organizations/B'Nai B'rith/Ararat Lodge/banquet, 1938
  - Other/Synagogues/Beth El/Sanctuary, undated
  - Other/Zionism/Inidviduals/Herzl, Theodore/print, undated